Guide to the Records of the New York University Self-Study 1953-1956 RG.15.5
New York University Archives
Records of the New York University Self-Study
1953-1956
New York University Archives
New York University
RG.15.5
7.5 Linear Feet (18 boxes)
The Records of the New York University Self-Study contain memoranda, correspondence, departmental evaluations and reports for the New York University Self-Study Final Report, published in 1956. The Self-Study marked the first serious attempt at comprehensive self-evaluation, and the results enabled the University to plan ahead for years to come. The material in this collection comprises the background to the Self-Study and includes material listed only in the appendices of the Final Report.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
The files are grouped into ten series:
Missing Title
Alphabetical Series Working Files
The Schools and Colleges of NYU
OIREP Internal Organization
OIREP Outgoing Reports
Alphabetical Series of Topics for Self-Study
Reference Material for Part I of The Final Report
Departmental Reports
Self-Study Conferences
Advisory Groups/Committees' Reports
Community Activities
Physical Access
Please note that this collection is stored offsite, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains seven and a half linear feet of background material and working papers that resulted in The New York University Self-Study Final Report, published in 1956.
Folders 1-57 contain mostly background material used by the OIREP, including a set of progress reports and the Interim Report. The Final Report was actually composed from files 58-194. These folders include 100 departmental reports given by faculty and chairmen of departments, which are only listed in Appendix A of the Final Report. The collection also includes reports of the nine conferences that proved crucial to the Self-Study.
History of the New York University Self-Study
The New York University Self-Study was proposed in 1952 by Dr. Henry T. Heald, then Chancellor of NYU, in a conversation with Mr. Charles Dollard, President of the Carnegie Corporation. A letter from Dr. Heald requesting a $250,000 grant from the Carnegie Corporation to fund the study explains the impetus behind such an undertaking. He writes:
"New York University is the largest privately supported institution of higher education in the country. The way in which it solves its problems will have meaning for higher education throughout the country and perhaps in other parts of the world. How best to meet the higher educational needs of Americans of the second half of the twentieth century in the large cities where most of the people now live and in large universities, to which most of our college students now go, is of fundamental significance to the future of America."
The study was administered by the Office of Institutional Research and Educational Planning (OIREP), established June 14, 1953, and the Directing Committee of the Self-Study. Faculty and administrators were asked to evaluate their departments. The study also incorporated evaluation of University-community relations and solicited evaluations by alumni. On September 27, 1955, the Self-Study Committee issued an Interim Report, which outlined many of the subjects covered by the Final Report. The Self-Study is significant in that it was the first time a large university, like NYU, undertook such a comprehensive self-evaluation.
This collection contains the background material for the self-study, including individual departmental reports, a series of working files, documents relating to the organization of OIREP, as well as conference reports and proceedings.
Sources:
New York University Self-Study Final Report, New York: New York University Press, 1956.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Provenance
This collection was brought together from the files of M. de Capriles, Director of the Office of Institutional Research and Educational Planning (OIREP), established at NYU in June 1953, and member of the Directing Committee of the Self-Study, and G.D. Stoddard, Chairman of the Directing Committee of the Self-Study. E.F. Knauth, staff assistant to de Capriles, organized the material and deposited it in the University Archives in 1975.
Reports.; Records surveys.; Correspondence.; Memorandums.; Proceedings.; Evaluation.; Publications (documents); Universities and Colleges -- Finance; Universities and colleges |z United States |x Administration.; Qualitative Analysis.; Universities and Colleges -- Curricula.; New York (N.Y.).; Capriles, Miguel Angel de; Knauth, Ernest Frederic, 1902-; Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townley), 1904-1975; New York University. Office of Institutional Research and Educational Planning; Stoddard, George Dinsmore, 1897-1981; New York University
- Series I: Alphabetical Working Files
  - Buffalo, University of, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042259039
  - Charitable Foundation Conference, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225903 9
  - Child Education Foundation, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings file, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - College Entrance Examination Board, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Commerce, School of, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Consultants, active, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Consultant, Robert D. Calkins, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Consultant, Donald H. Davenport, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Creative Arts, general, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Creative Arts, Columbia University, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Creative Arts, Ford Foundation, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Creative Arts, Rockefeller Committee, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Directing Committee, miscellaneous, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Directing Committee, Dr. Carter Davidson, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225904 7
  - Directing Committee, M. de Capriles, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Directing Committee, Dr. George Stoddard, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Directing Committee, Dr. Julius A. Stratton, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Education, School of, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Engineering, College of, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Evans, Ifor, Provost of University of London, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Fact Sheets on NYU, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Final Report, Publication of, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Final Report, Correspondence, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Final Report, Synopsis, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Final Report, Speeches, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Heald, Henry T., 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Interim Report, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Kastner, Elwood C., 1955 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225905 4
  - Lavenburg Corner House, 1945-1952 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Memoranda, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Middle States Association Survey of NYU 1949, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Office of Research Service Bulletins, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Pennsylvania, University of, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Public Administration and Social Service, Graduate School of, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Summer School, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Series II: The Schools and Colleges of NYU
  - Graduate Schools, University Commission on Graduate Work, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Graduate Schools, University Commission on Graduate Work, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Professional, College of Engineering, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Professional, College of Engineering, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Professional, School of Retailing, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Liberal Arts Colleges, University College of Arts and Sciences, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Liberal Arts Colleges, Washington Square College of Arts and Sciences, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Liberal Arts Colleges, Washington Square College of Arts and Sciences, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225906 2
  - Liberal Arts Colleges, Washington Square College of Arts and Sciences, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Series III: OIREP Internal Organization
  - Tentative Outlines, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Series IV: OIREP Outgoing Reports
  - Carnegie Corporation, 1952-1955 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Periodic Reports, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Series V: Alphabetical Series of Topics for Self-Study
  - Christ, Janer, Albert, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Enrollment, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Gould House, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - National Arts Center Association, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Packard Business School, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Projects, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Provost, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Residence Bureau, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Self-Survey NYU, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Series VI: Reference Material for Part I of The Final Report
  - Liberal Arts and Science, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Division of General Education, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225907 0
  - Creative Arts and Communications, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Library, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Library, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Press, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Student Activities, Extra-curricular, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Academic Council, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 65)
- Series VII: Departmental Reports
  - Washington Square College: Biology, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Washington Square College: Chemistry, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Washington Square College: Classics, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Washington Square College: Economics, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Washington Square College: English, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Washington Square College: Fine Arts, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Washington Square College: French, Italian, Russian - Language Lab Report, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 72A)
  - Washington Square College: French, Italian, Russian, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 72B)
  - Washington Square College: Geology, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Washington Square College: German, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Washington Square College: Government, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Washington Square College: History, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Washington Square College: Mathematics, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Washington Square College: Music, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Washington Square College: Physics, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Washington Square College: Psychology, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Washington Square College: Sociology and Anthropology, undated (Box 5, Folder 81A)
  - Washington Square College: Sociology and Anthropology, undated (Box 5, Folder 81B)
  - Washington Square College: Spanish and Portuguese, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225908 8
  - Washington Square College: Speech, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Science: Languages and Literature, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Science: Philosophy, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Science: Psychology, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Science: Economics, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Science: Government, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Science: History, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Science: Institute of Public Affairs and Regional Studies, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Science: Sociology, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Graduate School of Public Administration and Social Service, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Fine Arts, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Music, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - American Civilization Group, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Physics and Chemistry, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Biological Sciences, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Accounting, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Banking and Finance, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Business English, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Economics, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: General Course Group, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225909 6
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Law of Commerce and Finance, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Management and Industrial Relations, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Marketing, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Public Utilities and Transportation, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Real Estate, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance: Secretarial Studies, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - School of Education: Administration and Supervision, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - School of Education: Adult Education, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - School of Education: Business Education, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - School of Education: Center for Community and Field Services, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - School of Education: Center for Community and Field Services, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - School of Education: Center for Human Relations Studies, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - School of Education: Communications in Education, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - School of Education: Early Childhood and Elementary Education, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - School of Education: Educational Psychology, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 117)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225910 4
  - School of Education: Educational Sociology and Anthropology, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 118)
  - School of Education: English Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 119)
  - School of Education: Foreign Languages and Literature, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - School of Education: Guidance and Personnel Administration, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - School of Education: Hebrew Culture and Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - School of Education: Higher Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - School of Education: History of Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 124)
  - School of Education: Home Economics, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 125)
  - School of Education: Mathematics Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 126)
  - School of Education: Music Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - School of Education: Nurse Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 128)
  - School of Education: Philosophy of Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 129)
  - School of Education: Physical Education, Health, and Recreation, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 130)
  - School of Education: Religious Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - School of Education: Safety Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 132)
  - School of Education: Science Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - School of Education: Secondary Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - School of Education: Social Studies, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 135)
  - School of Education: Speech Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 136)
  - School of Education: Vocational Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 137)
  - School of Education: Report on Student Personnel Services, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 138)
  - School of Education: Freshmen Experimental Program, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 139)
  - General Supplementary Report: The School of Education, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 140)
  - Addition: The Report of the Committee to Study the Problems of Student Teachers, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - University College: Biology, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - University College: Chemistry, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - University College: Classics, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 144)
  - University College: English, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 145)
  - University College: German, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 146)
  - University College: History, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 147)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225911 2
  - University College: Music, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 148)
  - University College: Political Science, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 149)
  - University College: Psychology, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 150)
  - University College: Romance Languages and Literatures, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 151)
  - University College: General Supplementary Report: University College, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 152)
  - College of Engineering: Aeronautical Engineering, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - College of Engineering: Chemical Engineering, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 154)
  - College of Engineering: Civil Engineering, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 155)
  - College of Engineering: Electrical Engineering, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - College of Engineering: Engineering Mechanics and Engineering Drawing, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - College of Engineering: Industrial Management Engineering and Management Training, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 158)
  - College of Engineering: Mathematics, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 159)
  - College of Engineering: Mechanical Engineering, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 160)
  - College of Engineering: Meteorology and Oceanography, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 161)
  - Physical Training and Athletics, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 162)
  - Foreign Student Center (enrollment report), 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 163)
  - NYU Christian Association, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 164)
  - NYU Religious Association Committee, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 165)
- Series VIII: Self-Study Conferences
  - First Gould House Conference: Problems and Issues in Undergraduate Education at Washington Square, 1954 October 22-23 (Box 10, Folder 166)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225912 0
  - Second Gould House Conference: The Self-Study of the School of Law, 1954 December 17-18 (Box 10, Folder 167)
  - Third Gould House Conference: Problems and Issues in Arts and Sciences at NYU, 1955 January 14-15 (Box 11, Folder 168)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225913 8
  - Fourth Gould House Conference: School of Education, Problems and Issues, 1955 February 21 (Box 12, Folder 169)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225914 6
  - Fifth Gould House Conference: The Self-Study of the College of Engineering, 1955 February 4-5 (Box 13, Folder 170)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225915 3
  - Sixth Gould House Conference: University College Curriculum Commission, 1955 March 25-26 (Box 13, Folder 171)
  - Seventh Gould House Conference: Problems and Issues in Graduate Education and Research at NYU, 1955 May 15-16 (Box 14, Folder 172)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225916 1
  - Eighth Gould House Conference: Schools of Business Self-Study, 1955 May 6-7 (Box 15, Folder 173)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225917 9
  - Ninth Self-Study Conference: Washington Square College, 1956 January 25 (Box 15, Folder 174)
  - Comments Received from Conference Participants, undated (Box 15, Folder 175)
- Series IX: Advisory Groups/ Committee Reports
  - Advisory Group on Admissions, 1955-1956 (Box 15, Folder 176)
  - Advisory Group on Child Research Center, Feb 29, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 177)
  - Advisory Group on the Core Curriculum of the School of Education, 1954-1956 (Box 16, Folder 178)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225918 7
  - Committee on Education of Health Personnel, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 179)
  - Advisory Group on the Future in Education, 1955-1956 (Box 16, Folder 180)
  - Advisory Group on General or Basic Education, 1955-1956 (Box 16, Folder 181)
  - Advisory Group on General or Basic Education, 1955-1956 (Box 16, Folder 182)
  - Committee on International Affairs, 1955-1956 (Box 17, Folder 183)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225919 5
  - Advisory Group on Medical Affairs, Mar 13, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 184)
  - Modern Foreign Language Committee, 1954-1956 (Box 17, Folder 185)
  - Committee on Nurse Education, 1953-1956 (Box 17, Folder 186)
  - Advisory Group on Religion, 1955-1956 (Box 17, Folder 187)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Education Policy at Washington Square, Nov 10, 1955 (Box 18, Folder 188)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225920 3
  - Committee on University Health Services Combined with Committee to Select a Successor to Dr. Sawhill, as University Physician, 1954-1956 (Box 18, Folder 189)
  - Student Contributions, 1955-1956 (Box 18, Folder 190)
  - Alumni Saturday, May 1, 1954 (Box 18, Folder 191)
  - Alumni Reports: Alumni Visiting Committee of the Arts and Engineering Alumni; Commerce Alumni Association; Washington Square College Alumni Association; Graduate School of Business Administration Alumni Association, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 192)
- Series X: Community Activities
  - University Community Co-operation Project, 1953-1954 (Box 18, Folder 193)
  - American Community Filming, 1953-1954 (Box 18, Folder 194)